Elmer Gertz Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Elmer Gertz Papers 1789-1997 (bulk 1926-1988)
MSS22665
Gertz, Elmer, 1906-2000
168,725 items
484 containers plus 4 oversize
193 linear feet
1 microfilm reel
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer, author, and manuscript collector. Correspondence, memoranda, family papers, legal files, subject files, speeches, writings, manuscripts collected by Gertz, newspaper clippings, and printed matter relating primarily to Gertz’s career as a lawyer.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adamic, Louis, 1899-1951--Correspondence.; Anastaplo, George, 1925- --Correspondence.; Baldwin, James, 1924-1987.; Crandall, Allen, 1896-1973--Correspondence.; Crump, Paul--Correspondence.; Daley, Richard J., 1902-1976--Correspondence.; Daley, Richard M. (Richard Michael), 1942- --Correspondence.; Darrow, Clarence, 1857-1938.; Douglas, Alfred Bruce, 1870-1945--Correspondence.; Douglas, Paul H. (Paul Howard), 1892-1976--Correspondence.; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955--Correspondence.; Eisenschiml, Otto, 1880-1963--Correspondence.; Fink, Eli E., 1907-1979--Correspondence.; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939--Correspondence.; Gertz, Elmer, 1906-2000.; Gertz, Elmer, 1906-2000. Frank Harris: a study in black and white. 1931.; Gertz, Elmer, 1906-2000. Odyssey of a barbarian: the biography of George Sylvester Viereck. 1979.; Gertz, Theodore G.--Correspondence.; Giampietro, Wayne B. (Wayne Bruce), 1942- --Correspondence.; Goldberg, Arthur J., 1908-1990--Correspondence.; Harris, Frank, 1856-1931--Correspondence.; Harris, Frank, 1856-1931.; Hechtman, Margery A.--Correspondence.; Herman, Samuel G.--Correspondence.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963--Correspondence.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Leopold, Nathan Freudenthal, 1904-1971--Correspondence.; Leopold, Nathan Freudenthal, 1904-1971.; Levin, Meyer, 1905-1981.; Lovitz, Gene--Correspondence.; McWilliams, Carey, 1905-1980--Correspondence.; Meyer, Russ, 1922- --Correspondence.; Miller, Henry, 1891-1980--Correspondence.; Pearson, Hesketh, 1887-1964--Correspondence.; Peters, Muriel--Correspondence.; Pollack, Peter, 1909-1978--Correspondence.; Rosten, Leo, 1908-1997--Correspondence.; Ruby, Jack--Correspondence.; Ruby, Jack.; Ryan, William F. (William Fitts), 1922-1972--Correspondence.; Sandburg, Carl, 1878-1967--Correspondence.; Sandburg, Carl, 1878-1967.; Schwartz, Edward P.--Correspondence.; Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950.; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968--Correspondence.; Stephens, Kate, 1853-1938--Correspondence.; Tobin, A. I.--Correspondence.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Viereck, George Sylvester, 1884-1962--Correspondence.; Viereck, Peter, 1916-2006--Correspondence.; Witherspoon, William W.--Correspondence.
Organizations
Blind Service Association.; Caxton Club.; Chicago Bar Association.; Chicago Citizens Commission to Study the Disorders of Convention Week.; Decalogue Society of Lawyers.; Democratic National Convention (1968: Chicago, Ill.); Illinois Coalition Against the Death Penalty.; Illinois. Constitutional Convention (1969-1970); Robert Welch, Inc.--Trials, litigation, etc.
Subjects
American literature--20th century.; Capital punishment.; Censorship.; Copyright.; Housing.; Libel and slander.; Obscenity (Law); Practice of law--Illinois--Chicago.
Occupations
Authors.; Lawyers.
Provenance
The papers of Elmer Gertz, lawyer, author, and manuscript collector, were given to the Library of Congress between 1966 and 1997
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some photographs and drawings have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Motion picture films and sound and video recordings have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Elmer Gertz Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Elmer Gertz are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm copy of Sigmund Freud’s letters and messages to George Sylvester Viereck is available on one reel for use in the Manuscript Division subject to domestic copyright laws and international treaties and conventions. The microfilm is not available for purchase and may not be borrowed on interlibrary loan.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1906, Sept. 14 Born, Chicago, Ill.
1928 Ph.B., University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill.
1930 J.D., University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill.
1930 1941 Associate in law firm of McInerney, Epstein & Arvey, Chicago, Ill.
1931 Married Ceretta Samuels (died 1958) Published with A. I. Tobin Frank Harris: A Study in Black and White (Chicago: Madelaine Mendelsohn. 293 pp.)
1934 Director of public relations, Illinois Police Association
1941 1973 Attorney in private practice, Chicago, Ill.
1944 Member, Executive Committee, Illinois Committee for Equal Job Opportunity Member, national and Chicago Advisory Board Commission on Law and Social Action,; American Jewish Congress
1945 1947 Chairman, Veterans Housing Committee, Chicago, Ill.
1946 1948 Legislative chairman of Mayor's Emergency Housing Committee, Chicago, Ill.
1949 1951 Member, Mayor's Housing Action Committee, Chicago, Ill.
1959 Married Mamie L. Friedman
1959 1963 President, Greater Chicago Council of the American Jewish Congress
1965 Published A Handful of Clients (Chicago: Follett Publishing Co. 379 pp.)
1965 1969 President, Adult Education Council of Greater Chicago
1968 Member, Chicago Citizens Commission to Study the Disorders of Convention Week Published Moment of Madness: The People vs. Jack Ruby (Chicago: Follett Publishing Co. 564 pp.)
1969 1970 Delegate to the sixth Illinois Constitutional Convention; chairman of its Committee on Bill of Rights
1970 circa 1997 Professor, John Marshall Law School, Chicago, Ill.
1972 Awarded the state of Israel's Prime Minister's Medal Published For the First Hours of Tomorrow: The New Illinois Bill of Rights (Urbana: University of Illinois Press. 178 pp.
1973 Became partner in law firm of Gertz and Giampietro, Chicago, Ill.
1974 Successful plaintiff in landmark libel suit Gertz v. Robert Welch, Inc. Published To Life: The Story of a Chicago Lawyer (New York: McGraw-Hill Book Co. 308 pp.)
1975 Editor, The Short Stories of Frank Harris: A Selection (Carbondale: Southern Illinois University Press. 299 pp.)
1978 Editor, Henry Miller: Years of Trial and Triumph, 1962-1964: The Correspondence of Henry Miller and Elmer Gertz (Carbondale: Southern Illinois University Press. 345 pp.)
1978 1980 First Amendment Lawyers Association; president, 1978-1979; chairman, 1979-1980
1979 Published Odyssey of a Barbarian: The Biography of George Sylvester Viereck (Buffalo: Prometheus Books. 305 pp.)
1980 Published Charter for a New Age: An Inside View of the Sixth Illinois Constitutional Convention (Urbana: University of Illinois Press. 378 pp.)
1983 Published A Guide to Estate Planning (Carbondale: Southern Illinois University Press. 179 pp.)
1984 Published Quest for a Constitution: A Man Who Wouldn't Quit: A Political Biography of Samuel Witwer of Illinois (Lanham, Md.: University Press of America. 231 pp.)
1992 Published Gertz v. Robert Welch, Inc.: The Story of a Landmark Libel Case (Carbondale: Southern Illinois University Press. 295 pp.)
2000, Apr. 27 Died, Chicago, Ill.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Elmer Gertz (1906-2000) span the years 1789-1997, with the majority of the papers concentrated from 1926 to 1988. The bulk of the papers documents Gertz's career as a lawyer, author, and manuscript collector. The collection consists of eight series: Family Papers, General Correspondence, Legal File, Subject File, Speeches and Writings File, Miscellany, Addition, and Oversize.
The Family Papers series, 1926-1991, consists primarily of letters between Gertz and family members concerning personal matters. Gertz's letters to his children, Theodore G. Gertz and Margery A. Hechtman, often summarize his professional and personal activities, providing a glimpse of the attorney's busy schedule.
The papers in the General Correspondence series, 1925-1991, also chronicle Gertz's varied interests. Incoming and outgoing correspondence relates to personal and professional matters, including various commissions and organizations with which Gertz was associated. A few of the notable correspondents in this series are Louis Adamic,; Richard J. Daley,; Paul Howard Douglas,; Albert Einstein,; Eli E. Fink,; Arthur J. Goldberg,; Carey McWilliams,; Leo Calvin Rosten,; Carl Sandburg, and George Sylvester Viereck.
The Legal File, 1905-1992, constituting over half of the collection, documents Gertz's lengthy and prominent legal career. Papers in the series are divided into two subseries: Personal and Professional. The Personal subseries, 1950-1988, pertains to cases in which Gertz was a litigant. The private lawsuit which brought Gertz national attention was Gertz v. Robert Welch, Inc., a precedent-setting case which changed libel laws throughout the nation. The Chicago attorney sued the publishers of a John Birch Society publication for reporting that Gertz was involved in a Communist plot to discredit the Chicago Police Department. The United States Supreme Court ruled that Gertz, as a private individual, did not have to prove “actual malice” to receive compensatory damages.
The Professional subseries, 1905-1992, consists of correspondence and memoranda, chiefly between Gertz and clients, lawyers, and judges, as well as extensive legal files including opinions, orders, briefs, writs, motions, petitions, exhibits, and transcripts. Both case files and client files reflect the wide range of cases handled by Gertz, particularly those involving libel, obscenity, capital punishment, and copyright issues. One of Gertz's clients was novelist Henry Miller, who challenged charges that his work was obscene. Gertz fought successfully in Illinois against censorship of the writer's book Tropic of Cancer.
Another of Gertz’s clients, Nathan Freudenthal Leopold, was convicted with Richard Loeb of murdering fourteen-year-old Bobby Franks in a sensational trial that captivated the nation in 1924. Gertz later helped Leopold obtain a parole after thirty-four years in prison. Correspondence relating to Leopold's release is located in the early correspondence files of Leopold v. Levin, Leopold's suit seeking compensation from Meyer Levin, whose book and film, Compulsion, were based on the murder and subsequent trial. Background files for the Levin case also contain court documents and other material relating to Leopold's murder trial, Illinois v. Leopold.
Gertz was also one of a team of lawyers representing Jack Ruby, who was convicted of killing Lee Harvey Oswald, assassin of President John F. Kennedy, in November 1963. Gertz joined the defense team in December 1964 and assisted with Ruby's appeal which succeeded in getting his death sentence set aside. Several items in the Ruby v. Texas case file are worthy of mention: Ruby's letter to his brother Earl, located in the folder "Miscellaneous, 1964-70, undated"; Ruby's note to Gertz of 9 September 1965, located in the folder "Correspondence, Aug.-Sept. 1965"; and a reporter's note to Gertz describing his visit with Ruby shortly before Ruby's death, located in the folder "Correspondence, Mar.-Aug. 1967, undated" Additional material pertaining to Ruby may be found in the Speeches and Writings File relating to Gertz’s book Moment of Madness: The People vs. Jack Ruby.
Papers in the Subject File series, 1894, 1903-1990, illustrate Gertz's diverse interests and activities. This series chronicles his service with committees and organizations and documents his duties as a delegate and committee chair of the Illinois constitutional convention, 1969-1970; his work with the Chicago Bar Association, 1977-1985 and the Illinois Coalition Against the Death Penalty, 1977-1985; and his membership on the Chicago Citizens Commission to Study the Disorders of Convention Week (1968 Democratic national convention). Also reflected in the series is Gertz's interest in various historical and literary figures: James Baldwin,; Clarence Darrow,; Frank Harris,; John F. Kennedy,; Henry Miller,; Carl Sandburg,; Harry S. Truman, and Bernard Shaw. Other topics prominently featured include censorship, housing, obscenity, and the death penalty. There is some overlap between this series and the General Correspondence series, and many of the same individuals appear in both series. Also included are legal papers relating to Gertz's consultations in his later years.
The Speeches and Writings File, 1888-1990, document Gertz’s activities as a prolific writer and speaker interested not only in legal matters but in literary subjects as well. Some of his most voluminous papers relate to two of his books, Frank Harris: A Study in Black and White and Odyssey of a Barbarian: The Biography of George Sylvester Viereck. Gertz corresponded with both Harris and Viereck and accumulated a large amount of research material pertaining to each, including some of their original manuscripts, numerous autograph letters, and notes from prominent literary figures. The Viereck research material includes one reel of microfilm of original material not in the collection, letters and messages of Sigmund Freud to Viereck. Other books by Gertz include A Handful of Clients, a description of some of the attorney's more interesting clients, and To Life, an account of his personal and professional life.
The Miscellany series, 1789, 1860-1991, consists chiefly of manuscripts and printed matter collected by Gertz, which complement material in the Speeches and Writings File and pertain to his general research interests. Also included in the series are papers relating to his academic career and his awards and honors.
The Addition series supplements previous installments of the Gertz Papers and span the years 1921-1997, with the bulk concentrated from 1989-1996. The Addition includes correspondence, memoranda, family papers, legal files, subject files, and writings. The subject file, comprising almost half of the addition, reflects Gertz’s affiliation with organizations such as the Blind Service Association, the Caxton Club, and the Decalogue Society of Lawyers. Also documented in the subject file is Gertz’s interest in writers Frank Harris and George Sylvester Viereck and the assassination of John F. Kennedy. The writings file in the Addition relates primarily to Gertz v. Robert Welch, Inc. and the revised 1990 edition of Gertz’s memoir To Life. This file also includes a number of articles and book reviews that Gertz wrote for Real Crime Book Digest.
Among the most prominent and frequent correspondents are George Anastaplo,; Allen Crandall,; Paul Crump,; Richard M. Daley,; Lord Alfred Bruce Douglas,; Otto Eisenschiml,; Wayne B. Giampietro,; Frank Harris,; Samuel G. Herman,; John F. Kennedy,; Nathan Leopold,; Gene Lovitz,; Russ Meyer,; Henry Miller,; Hesketh Pearson,; Muriel Peters,; Peter Pollack,; Jack Ruby,; William F. Ryan,; Edward P. Schwartz,; Upton Sinclair,; Kate Stephens,; A. I. Tobin,; George Sylvester Viereck,; Peter Robert Edwin Viereck, and William W. Witherspoon.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in eight series:
Family Papers, 1926-1991
General Correspondence, 1925-1991
Legal File, 1905-1992
Subject File, 1894, 1903-1990
Speeches and Writings File, 1888-1990
Miscellany, 1789, 1860-1991
Addition, 1921-1997
Oversize, 1957, 1967
Container List
- Family Papers, 1926-1991 (Box 1-4)
  Correspondence between Gertz and family members with attachments and enclosures. Other papers include estate papers, invitations, notes, genealogical material, writings, newspaper clippings, and printed matter.
  Arrangement is alphabetical by type of material and therein alphabetical by name of family member.
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Friedman, Jack M. (stepson), 1963-1979, undated
    - Friedman, Jack M., Theodore G. Gertz (son), and Margery A. Hechtman (daughter), 1944, 1961-1968, undated
    - Gertz, Ceretta (wife)
      - 1927-1952, (7 folders)
      - Undated (Box 2)
    - Gertz, Mamie (wife), 1964-1986, undated
    - Gertz, Theodore G.
      - 1947-1962, (10 folders)
      - 1962-1991, undated, (4 folders) (Box 3)
    - Hechtman, Margery A., 1950-1991, undated, (6 folders)
    - Other relatives
      - 1947-1984, (5 folders)
      - 1985-1990, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Other papers
    - Friedman, Oscar (Mamie Gertz's first husband), estate papers, 1964-1970
    - Gertz, Ceretta, death of, 1958
    - Gertz, Morris A. (father), 1951-1953
    - Gertz, Theodore G., poetry, 1948-1958, undated, (2 folders)
    - Miscellaneous, 1926-1978, undated, (5 folders)
- General Correspondence, 1925-1991 (Box 5-13)
  Correspondence and memoranda, including attachments, between Gertz and friends, acquaintances, clients, and the public relating to his personal and professional activities.
  Arrangement is alphabetical by name of person, organization, or topic and therein chronological.
  - Abel, Wilma Reynolds, 1948-1949, undated (Box 5)
  - Adamic, Louis, 1926-1951, undated
  - American Jewish Congress, 1950-1980 See also Containers 304-307, same heading
  - Andrews, Wayne, 1947-1984 See also Container 307, same heading
  - Arvey, Jacob, 1934-1988, undated
  - “A” miscellaneous, 1929-1991, undated, (4 folders)
  - Barr, Stephen, 1945-1959, undated, (2 folders)
  - “B” miscellaneous, 1925-1991, undated, (4 folders)
  - Commission on Human Relations, Chicago, Ill., 1947-1956 (Box 6)
  - Congratulatory correspondence, 1931
  - “C” miscellaneous, 1929-1988, undated, (3 folders)
  - Daley, Richard J., 1953-1967, undated
  - Douglas, Paul Howard, 1948-1966, undated
  - Douglas, William O., 1955-1957, undated
  - “D” miscellaneous, 1926-1989, undated, (3 folders)
  - Einstein, Albert, 1954 See also Container 323, same heading
  - Eisenschiml, Otto, 1947-1970, undated For additional material see Container 58, same heading; Containers 59-62, Eisenschiml v. Fawcett Publications; and Container 63, Eisenschiml v. Parade Publications
  - English, Maurice, 1936-1979
  - “E” miscellaneous, 1930-1991, (2 folders)
  - Farrar, Geraldine, 1932, 1967
  - Fink, Eli E., 1928-1971 See also Container 324, same heading (Box 7)
  - “F” miscellaneous, 1929-1991, (4 folders)
  - Goldberg, Arthur J., 1956-1988
  - Grabitz, James, 1950-1978, undated, (3 folders)
  - Green, Gilbert, 1961, undated
  - Guthman, Seymour S., 1930-1983
  - “G” miscellaneous, 1927-1986, (3 folders)
  - Heller, Selig, 1956-1957, undated See also Container 86, same heading
  - Henriquez, Fiore de, 1961-1966 (Box 8)
  - Herman, Ben, 1931-1933
  - Herman, Samuel G., 1930-1988, undated For additional material see Containers 466-467, same heading, (3 folders)
  - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1948 See also Container 335, same heading
  - “H” miscellaneous, 1926-1989, undated, (2 folders)
  - Independent Voters of Illinois, 1949-1950, undated
  - “I” miscellaneous, 1932-1988, undated
  - “J” miscellaneous, 1929-1989
  - Klotzer, Charles L., 1961-1964, undated (Box 9)
  - “K” miscellaneous, 1929-1988, (3 folders)
  - Leiser, Clara, 1945, undated
  - Lerner, Leo, 1944-1965, undated
  - Lohman, Joseph D., 1954-1960, undated
  - Lovitz, Gene, 1971-1979 See also Containers 358-359, same heading; for additional material see Container 408, “Death Row;” and Containers 451-454, Sandburg
  - “L” miscellaneous, 1939-1989, undated, (3 folders)
  - McWilliams, Carey, 1955-1966, undated See also Containers 360-361, same heading
  - Meites, Irving J., 1956-1962, undated
  - Mendelsohn, Felix, 1930-1933
  - Mitchell, Stephen A., 1952-1960, undated, (2 folders)
  - Murphy, Michael, 1939, 1978-1981
  - “M” miscellaneous, 1928-1990, (4 folders) (Box 10)
  - National Society of Autograph Collectors, 1948-1952, undated
  - Newman, Ralph G., 1946-1979, undated
  - Northwestern University, Evanston, Ill., 1954-1978
  - “N” miscellaneous, 1926-1988, undated
  - “O” miscellaneous, 1948-1977, undated
  - Pierce, Rose Brandzel, 1954-1988
  - Poli, Carlo E., 1984, (3 folders)
  - “P” miscellaneous, 1926, 1933-1988 (Box 11)
  - “Q” miscellaneous, 1953-1981
  - Reich, John, 1977-1985, undated
  - Roosevelt University, Chicago, Ill., 1948-1976 See also Containers 368-369, same heading
  - Rosary College, Forest River, Ill., 1975-1985
  - Rosten, Leo Calvin, 1931-1985, undated, (2 folders)
  - “R” miscellaneous, 1947-1986, (2 folders)
  - Samuels, Alvin and Shirley, 1928, 1947-1991
  - Sandburg, Carl, 1930-1955 See also Container 370, same heading; for additional material see Containers 451-454, Sandburg
  - Saperstein, Esther, 1956-1962, undated For additional material see Container 6, Douglas, Paul Howard; see also Container 371, same heading
  - Schlosser, Louis L., Jr., 1978-1988
  - Schwartz, Edward P., 1964-1985, undated See also Containers 371-372, same heading
  - Sentman, Everett Edgar, 1975-1980
  - Simon, Seymour F., 1962-1988
  - Stevenson for President Committee, 1948-1965, undated
  - Stouder, Allan L., 1976
  - “S” miscellaneous, 1931-1991, (4 folders) (Box 12)
  - Tebbel, John, 1943-1947, undated
  - “T” miscellaneous, 1934-1983, (4 folders)
  - “U” miscellaneous, 1929-1988
  - Viereck, George Sylvester, 1953-1955 For additional material see Containers 435-449, Odyssey of a Barbarian, (3 folders)
  - “V” miscellaneous, 1932-1978 (Box 13)
  - “W” miscellaneous, 1943-1984, undated, (3 folders)
  - “Y-Z” miscellaneous, 1948-1982, undated
  - Unidentified, 1928-1988, undated, (2 folders)
- Legal File, 1905-1992 (Box 13-300)
  - Personal, 1950-1988 (Box 13-18)
    Correspondence, memoranda, briefs, orders, opinions, motions, reports, financial papers, statements, background information, and printed matter pertaining to legal cases in which Gertz was a litigant.
    Arrangement is alphabetical by case name.
    - Chicago Council of Lawyers v. Bauer, 1970-1971, (3 folders) (Box 13)
    - Connaughton v. Gertz, 1968, 1977-1981, (4 folders) (Box 14)
    - Gertz v. Bass
      - Financial papers, 1952-1963, (2 folders)
      - General, 1956-1965, (2 folders)
    - Gertz v. Chapin, 1950-1952
    - Gertz v. Colormedia Communications Corp., 1971-1972 (Box 15)
    - Gertz v. Kohlberg Theaters
      - Background information, 1970
      - Correspondence, 1970-1972, (2 folders)
      - Court documents, 1970-1971, undated, (2 folders)
      - General, 1971-1972
    - Gertz v. Myers, 1975
    - Gertz v. Robert Welch, Inc. See also Containers 417-418, same heading
      - Correspondence
        - 1974-1978, (4 folders)
        - 1979-1988, (12 folders) (Box 16)
      - General, 1965-1988, undated, (5 folders) (Box 17)
    - Gertz v. State Bd. of Elections, 1975-1977, (3 folders)
    - Walker v. Thompson, 1980-1982, (6 folders) (Box 18)
  - Professional, 1905-1992 (Box 18-300)
    Correspondence, memoranda, orders, opinions, briefs, writs, motions, petitions, financial papers, exhibits, depositions, transcripts, reports, notes, interviews, architectural plans and specifications, contracts, statements, writings, printed matter, and background information relating to Gertz's professional activities and interests.
    Arrangement is alphabetical by case name, client name, or subject, with the majority of the files further arranged by type of material.
    - A & L Demirdjian, Inc. v. Korean Karate Inst. (Box 18)
      - Background information, 1967, undated, (2 folders)
      - Billing, 1968 (Box 19)
      - Correspondence, 1967-1968